[Music]
I offer my
resense to the Divine in
[Applause]
you I'm going to
cover an U important topic
today it's about
[Applause]
relationships they are not new to you
interestingly
um most
people
their life revolves around
[Applause]
relationships
but and
overwhelming
majority are not happy with the uh state
of their
relationships so I'm going to cover the
spiritual
side or call the uh the yogic or the
meditational
side of
relationships as well as the Practical
side so let's
start what is a
relationship is it a
transaction is
relationship a
transaction of of uh
[Applause]
convenience of
needs of
desires or is
it a
bond Bond of uh
love does a relationship
come about because there is a
bond or because there is a
need in other words I'm
asking is it because of the
bonds
that people share common needs and
therefore a
relationship or is it because of of the
needs that they get into a
relationship and uh form a
bond the notion in the west is uh
somewhat different to what is in the
East although it is a uh stereotypical
statement so therefore it is not the
complete
truth but in the
East the concept of arranged
marriage is uh still quite
prevalent it is based on the belief that
two people can find a common
ground and be
committed to a
[Applause]
relationship the
educated people whether in the East or
the
West believe that they must find common
ground before they can commit to a
relationship when a relationship is born
out of
need clearly it is uh a selfish
relationship and may
just wither away when needs are
fulfilled when the relationship is the
result of a bond two people
[Applause]
share it tends to last longer
however I am not suggesting that they
are mutually
exclusive it
is
possible that two people have a common
set of
needs as well as a
[Applause]
bond but
often you find people
not happy they are
often wanting
more and uh what is funny
is they justify they're wanting more by
saying that what they want is actually
just what they want is not
[Applause]
much but the key to remember is that is
your your
Viewpoint that Viewpoint may not be
shared by your
partner the greater the
disparity in that
[Applause]
Viewpoint the
uh more Fragile the
bond people talk about love and people
talk about relationship and people talk
about being in love and out of love and
falling in love and
loving and the differentiation in all
these
[Applause]
terms however I
Feel Love is a term that has been used
and
abused so
much that it almost now means all those
things it is not
[Applause]
love is
independent if nature loves
you it gives you rain
regardless it gives you food
regardless it is not saying to you if
you don't love
me I am not going
to to give you that I used to give you
and that is the fundamental difference
between
love and a
transaction when a relationship is a
transaction it's just a convenient
transaction it's just an
institution then both people are pretty
much competing for their
needs and that is the the irony of uh
this
world from every since you can
recall you have been
taught to
compete for everything you got in life
you pretty much had
to work for it you pretty much had to
work towards it and you pretty much had
to compete for
it however love is not about
competition love is not about give and
take
I know you may not agree with me on this
one right
now but if we purely look at the concept
of love the definition of
love believe it or not love is not a
give and take
proposition love is actually about
giving giving love giving Freedom giving
that person person
space and something I've
said earlier as well in some of the
other uh
talks
that when you give something out lets
its
love you may not get love back from the
same
person why because love is not a
reciprocal arrangement with an
individual
it is with God it is with
nature so if you are giving out
love nature will certainly most
definitely you
can basically it's like written on the
on on the stone will give you love
back if you are giving love to your
husband or your
spouse they may not be the on giving you
love back directly but you may
get in
multiple and multifold from
your
children or from other
people and love is of two
types one that is spontaneously out of
you the other one that you make an ATT
attempt to
show sometimes when relations go
sour
people have to work towards people have
to work together to be back in
love it is often a hard
[Applause]
thing and it is hard not because it is
not
doable but because it is based on
expectations on
desires and both expectations and
desires are a product are products of
the conditioned
minds they're all based on on
conditioning some
religion may allow you to
have three wives for
example
whereas many others will regarded as
illegal and
immoral so what is right and what is
wrong there is no independent definition
of this it is all
[Applause]
subjective from a practical stand point
of
view when you start to say what about
me chances are you're already late in
the equation you're
already at a point where you feel that
things need some serious
overhaul in the relationship that
is because when you are saying what
about
me that means either you feel it is not
a fair
relationship or you feel
neglected basically at that point in
time you feel lack of
fulfillment if we start to delve deeper
into the causes of such
disharmony between two
people we can uh keep
counting till eternity and we'll still
have more
reasons if you look at the spiritual
side you will know what I
mean from
the spiritual point of
view when you love
somebody and you expect something back
in
return that is not
love and I give you the right to
disagree
totally but I hope by the end of this
talk when you've had the time
to to think about
things it may actually make sense to
you when you want something in
return and you giving love because you
want love in
return you you have just created
yourself an
illusion an illusion of
love love is not about getting things
back love is just about giving to begin
with and doing so
without
expectations when you start to give
you will start to open
up and that is going to set the ball
rolling for many many many beautiful and
divine things to flourish in your
[Applause]
life how you justify your expectations
is your personal
matter but from the perspective of
meditation from the perspective of
self-realization or
spirituality there is never ever any
justification for any
expectation whatsoever at
all expectation
are a product of the conditioned
mind it is your conditioning
conditioning of the self of the soul of
the mind you can give it whatever term
you want to give that prompt you to
expect you expect out of a relationship
because that is all you have
seen that is how you saw your parents
possibly or or other relatives or the
preceding Generations
because you you that's all you've been
taught and that's all what you have uh
observed and uh
absorbed it is only natural that you
expect so whether your expectation is
Justified or not I want to keep that
aside for a moment I just want to look
at the consequences of having
expectations at the first
place when you desire an
outcome when you want your part partner
to reciprocate in kind you have just
created
yourself
bondage for yourself bondage now that is
going
to enfet you uh basically tie you down
and unshackle you for sure have no
doubts on that
front because now your happiness is
dependent on the reaction or the
respiration from somebody from from the
other person now you've just created
[Applause]
dependency on something
external and there
starts the beginning
of non-fulfillment
so is it possible to be only giving in a
relationship and not
expect well anything is possible
actually is it right
you're not actually going to accept my
answer on that
one because it is not about right or
wrong I'm
only looking at your
happiness if you want
unconditioned and unconditional
happiness you have to give
unconditionally
when you seow a seed in the
ground does it sprout right away or does
it take some
time from what I know it always takes
some
time so there is no quick fix when you
start to
give and you make resolution that okay
from today onwards I'm just going to be
giving and let me see how long it is
before nature starts giving me back well
actually that is the beginning of an of
an expectation
again just
give just
try okay give yourself a reasonable time
frame 6 months 1 year or something like
that the problem comes when you say I
did that you know in the past
but he still did not
bother my husband or my wife my my
spouse my partner still did not
change but there's a
problem you started giving with the uh
with the expectation at the first place
and that is exactly what we need to
avoid
here we are not saying that here's a way
to get love back from
people I'm saying here's a way to be
happy to be at
peace because if you are peaceful inside
and if you are happy
inside your life will
become fulfilling
automatically
automatically there will be no
competition at that point in
time you will not be competing with no
one for
love why because the infinite source of
bliss is actually within
you all the love you can possibly
want REM
imagine is within
you you want things from the external
world because you have not started
tapping into your inner
World your communication with the inner
world is actually broken
down so that is why you turn outward for
everything whether that is joy happiness
love satisfaction
gratification you name it
anything and because everything
outside is
scarce
interdependent and
conditional therefore you're always
having to
compete and that exercise it's like
ranging the uh Universe from one end to
the other it is a NeverEnding
exercise you can be married to somebody
for 40
years for 30 years for 50
years and still actually feel that sense
of non-fulfillment or
unfulfillment or
both why because all these years chances
are you actually did not have a bond as
such you merely curved your expectations
you merely curved your desires you put a
lid on what you
wanted and because you put a lid on what
you
wanted you may have projected to the
outside world
as a uh you know happy couple or happy
person but the fact is deep within you
you're not
happy because nobody can be happy by
curbing their desires you have to
understand the nature of the desires you
have to understand
the the nature of
yourself and then Bliss will gush forth
automatically because your true nature
is
bliss and that is what's key to remember
so how can you get to
[Applause]
Bliss and how can you discover your real
nature once again
I have to tell you there is no Quick Fix
You Can intellectually calm yourself
down you can uh artificially make
yourself believe that I no longer want
anything but you and I both know that is
not going to help
you and that is also not the
truth because just saying I don't want
anything will not make you feel not
wanted
you actually have to not want
it and it is possible
how I will get to that in a
moment you see because of your
conditioning like I said earlier and
because you watch everything from the
external World from everything that is
outside you want to experience
everything through the body
you want good
food good clothes good shelter and good
society and and the rest of
it but that is all external they are
only designed to make your body look a
certain
way your fulfillment actually comes
from
emotions and you can think about it
deeply
and you will find yourself in agreement
with to what I'm
saying so that fulfillment is always
from within it is not from outside it's
not from without it is
within so sooner or
later you have to turn inward you
basically have two
choices you can keep riding the roller
coaster of of Joys and Sorrows of the
material
world or you can turn
inward and find that permanent state of
Happiness when you
find
your
true
nature
when your journey of self-discovery
finishes your energy is going to be so
purified it is going to be so magnetic
so charismatic so enigmatic
that not just your partner but
everybody will only ever offer you
love and that is what I mean and that is
what I'm getting at that you need to get
to a stage within you that your
happiness is no longer dependent on
external things and when you get to that
stage you will get so much of external
happiness does that mean it is not long
it is no longer going to matter at that
point in time
no what it means is you will become so
pure that you will totally
enjoy every moment of your
life you will have learned to
live you will have learned to
love you will have learned
to
laugh at things at life at yourself
that is the true
you the true you is not a mother or a
wife or a daughter or a
uh uh a worker or a manager or a
[Music]
CEO the true you is bliss the true you
is hiding in you the true you is hiding
behind
your emotional self
[Applause]
so you need to spend some time analyzing
yourself if a
shortterm solution happiness or Joy or
give it any name you want is more
important to
you and you don't want to work towards
your own self-realization or that state
where you feel that
Bliss then there is not much I can
do then it's going to pretty much keep
on going the way it is
going you will have happy days and you
will have sad days you will have days of
joy and days of
Sorrow you will have your share of
sunshine and uh your share of
rain there'll be sunny days and there'll
be muggy weather
but if
you always only want one
thing and that is
joy and you want to become so that
anybody who gets in touch with you can
only ever feel love for
you then that is in your
hands whether in today's date
other people love you or
not whether your partner loves you the
same way as you love him or
her is not in your
hands
because if you feel that they don't love
you as
much for the way you are presently
then I can guarantee
you it will not matter what you
do they will not start loving you
more those who love you if they cannot
accept you the way you
are if they
cannot accept who you are what you are
and where you are in your life
they will never accept you because it is
not love at the first place when it is
conditional when they have imposed a
condition fulfillment of which is the
criteria for their loving
you it is not love my
friend think about it
and you know it goes for you as
well if you cannot accept your partner
the
way the he or she is and if you
cannot love them for who they
are they can become God you still will
not be able to love
them that is the truth of false
love because when you
love it is not
conditional if you have a
pet and you love that
pet that pet communicates with you but
only very
limited in a very
confined
manner but you still love of that
pet your dog is not going out there 9
to5 earning money for you or paying the
bills but you don't hate your dog for
that
why
because maybe it is far-fetched
yet it's the truth because you've
accepted
it because you have never seen a dog
working in earning
money so you have accepted that when a
dog is going to be at home you'll have
to feed him and you'll have to clean up
after
him but when it comes to other human
beings in the family suddenly your
expectations go through the
roof why do you have a very good reason
for
it you may have
a ton of very good
excuses or
justifications but you are not going to
have any reason for
it
why because love is Beyond
Reason when a relationship is
underscored by
love it is always going to be Rock Solid
when it
is held together by
needs it is not going to last very
long when it is the result of some
bond which is dependent on both
parties it
has some chances of survival
I know you have been trained to ask the
question why
me in fact what about me more
importantly is a question you ask in a
relationship there are two things you
need to
do
first is you somehow have to find
time to
meditate so
that you can start cleaning
yourself your inner self your real
self so you can remove layers and layers
of
conditioning as you move closer to
selfis
Discovery your
relationships are going
to
improve
infinitely infinite times
more than you can
imagine because when you start to gain
that inner
stability I am not saying that
your partner will suddenly start loving
you a lot
more but when you start to gain that
inner
stability you will start to
see light from
dark trees from Woods
and you will start to make your
choices lot more
intelligently as well
as
naturally nature is going to start
working with
you you will find yourself less and less
in undesirable situations
and that is how your life is going to
change you may still choose to move
on but
your next decision your next
choice is not going
to give you
grief because one you have turned inward
word you have discovered your source of
place therefore super
knowledge
will automatically
Blossom it's a byproduct of
self-realized Person of self-realization
sorry I should
say so when you start to make choices
lot more conducive to
love you
will start to get lot more
love but I have to say it again that
your journey is not about getting love
from
outside it is about discovering The Love
Inside you can keep going to counseling
you can
keep on trying patching your
relationships or you can keep moving
between
relationships or start forming new ones
but all of these will not help
you because if you are not
happy I'm sorry to tell you this but if
you are not happy it is your problem
it is you who needs fixing it is you who
needs to make a trip to the
garage and get
serviced because your
nonha is due to your own state of
mind sometimes people go through a
divorce
and the person the divorce when that
person gets into a new
relationship often
is I'm not sure if I can use the word
often but
generally is a happier
person it is not uncommon to hear that
the the person they have now married
they are actually quite happy but you
are not and you may have married married
another person but you're still not
happy what does that tell
you and if your relationship is because
of fulfillment of certain needs then
stop
complaining if your needs are being met
if
you are getting financially taken care
of and the rest of it is then you really
don't have a reason to complain
because subconsciously chances are you
actually knew from day one that this
relationship is not because of a bond it
is not because of
love
but it is like I say a convenient
transaction now you have to accept
it just because you have changed your
mind
Now does not mean that the other person
is
terrible it is you who we are concerned
with and it is you who we have to work
with so you need to find the time to
meditate till such time that you start
to quiet quieten your
mind you are not ready to do self
analysis believe it or not
today if you sit down to do self
analysis chances are you cannot stay on
a thought for more than 3
seconds your emotional turmoil your
inner
turmoil will
overtake as soon as you sit down and
start to perform self analysis if I ask
you okay make a list of all the things
you don't like in your partner
I promise you before you can finalize
the
list you would
have let so much of
anger and
frustration grow and come out of you
grow in you and come out of you
that you will be swept
away you will not be able to know
what
exactly is it that actually bothers
you to carry out penetrating
analysis your mind must be
settled and if your analysis is
shaky your
choices will be like that too it is only
natural isn't it
so you need to turn
inward right now you want all the
answers from the world outside and you
want to grasp
everything from here using
this
but it is not the reason you are in a
relationship this is and this is where
you need to go
go in go
inside take a
dive see what you see
there feel what you feel
there
you will be
amazed you will get
answers to questions you never
thought could even be possible
so in
summary you cannot make a relationship
good by negating your
desires that is out of
question that is first second you cannot
change the other
person third your state of
happiness is your creation
and is entirely dependent on
you
fourth moving from one relationship to
the other or getting into a new one may
offer you temporary
Comfort but eventually it is going to
be like your present
relationship fifth you need to turn
inward to discover your source of
place upon
which your Viewpoint your
perspective to look at the world people
things relationships
achievements gains loss emotions
everything is going to change completely
and the changed
you is going to
be a billion times happier than the
present
you that is what uncond conditioning
does you start to see needs versus
desires versus
expectations you start to see
emotions in their truest
sense for what they are
and you start to see
people as pure
place it is
possible but not without effort you have
to put in the
effort that is all I have for you today
get
[Music]